Guide to the Lavater Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lavater collection.
1775-1816
YCGL MSS 13
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.97
(3 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
Collection of engravings, drawings, silhouettes, and miniature paintings, many of them annotated in the hand of Johann Caspar Lavater. The artists most heavily represented among the signed works in the collection are Daniel Chodowiecki and Johann Heinrich Lips, both major contributors to Lavater's Physiognomische Fragmente.
Lavater, Johann Caspar, 1741-1801
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The provenance of the collection is uncertain, although it may have been part of the material, called simply "prints," purchased in 1926 from descendants of Lavater, Waldemar C. Hirschfeld (Yale certificate in architecture, 1903) and his brother Robert Lavater Hirschfeld, both then of Meriden, Connecticut.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
JOHANN CASPAR LAVATER (1741-1801)
Johann Caspar Lavater was born in Zürich in 1741, the son of a physician. He trained as a clergyman and at the beginning of his career campaigned successfully against corruption in the government of the canton. Having made many local enemies during this controversy, he undertook a journey with his friend Heinrich Füssli through northern Germany, where he met several prominent authors and public figures. Upon his return to Switzerland, he became increasingly well known as an eloquent preacher, which led finally to his appointment as deacon (1778) and then pastor (1786) of St. Peter's Church in Zürich. His later years were overshadowed by political events. Because of his outspoken criticism of the government, he came under suspicion of collaboration with Russia and Austria and was arrested in May 1799 and deported to Basel. Released in June, he returned to Zürich where, in September, he was himself wounded while trying to help wounded soldiers during the occupation of the city by the French. His injuries resulted in a long and painful illness, of which he died on 2 January 1801.
Lavater's numerous published works include poems, prose works devoted to his emotional, pietistic brand of Christianity, and the famous Physiognomische Fragmente, published in four volumes between 1775 and 1778 and illustrated with many engravings. Lavater's friendship with Goethe began by letter in 1772. They first met in 1774, and, as is well known, Goethe made minor contributions to the Physiognomische Fragmente. The friendship cooled during the early 1780s as Goethe became alienated by Lavater's growing religious fanaticism.
Scope and Contents
Many of the engravings, drawings, and miniature paintings in this collection are annotated in the hand of Johann Caspar Lavater (1741-1801). The style of some of the drawings, as well as the format of the material (for example, the way the illustrations are mounted and the style of the borders, both handmade and engraved) resemble two other manuscripts in the Speck Collection, Lavater's "Vermischte physiognomische Regeln" (YCGL MSS 6, vol. 819, from 1789) and his "Stufen" (YCGL MSS 6, vol. 820a-c). It would appear that at least some of the present material represents fragments and/or rejected portions from the process of creating collections similar to the two just named. Lavater's habit of assembling sets of aphorisms and emblematic illustrations for his family and friends is well known.
Of the dated items, almost all fall in the 1790s, the majority in the second half of that decade. The collection is organized into three series: Portraits, Other Artwork, and Other Papers. Portraits is organized into Potraits of Johann Caspar Lavater and Portraits of Others. Other Artwork is organized into eight subseries: Jacques Callot, Daneil Chodowiecki, Johann Heinrich Lips, Conrad Meyer, Pfenninger, del., George Friedrich Schmol, Various Artists, and Unidentified.
The artists most heavily represented among the signed engravings in the collection are Daniel Chodowiecki (1726-1801) and Johann Heinrich Lips (1758-1817), both major contributors to the work for which Lavater is best remembered, Physiognomische Fragmente zur Beförderung des Menschenkenntnis und Menschenliebe. The collection includes a small portrait of Anna Barbara Schulthess (1745-1818), a friend of Goethe who preserved the manuscript of Wilhelm Meisters theatralische Sendung (the first version of Wilhelm Meisters Lehrjahre ), not rediscovered and published until 1911 (folder 10). Other notable items include a silhouette of Katharina von Stolberg (1751-1832), sister of the poets Christian and Friedrich Leopold von Stolberg, and a self-portrait by the painter Johann Caspar Schinz (1797-1832), a pupil of Heinrich Lips (folders 11 and 6).
The collection was previously housed in a large box labeled "Lavater" that had been among the uncataloged holdings of the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana for several decades. Possibly the collection was not cataloged by earlier librarians because of the fragmentary nature of its contents. The provenance of the collection is uncertain, although it may have been part of the material, called simply "prints," purchased in 1926 from descendants of Lavater, Waldemar C. Hirschfeld (Yale certificate in architecture, 1903) and his brother Robert Lavater Hirschfeld, both then of Meriden, Connecticut. Later the Hirschfelds donated to the Speck Collection oil portraits of Lavater by Ilg and of Gottlieb Wilhelm Rabener (1714-71) by Anton Graff. The exact relationship between Lavater and the Hirschfelds has not at this writing been determined. Their father was Henry Hirschfeld, one of four sons of a widow Hirschfeld who immigrated to the United States from Emmershausen around 1850. Heinrich Fussli's drawing of Mrs. Lavater's hands, now at the Beinecke Library, came from the Hirschfeld family as well; in 1926 it was described as still being in the possession of an unnamed aunt of Waldemar and Robert Hirschfeld.
Engravings (prints); Etchings (prints); Silhouettes; Watercolors (paintings); Chodowiecki, Daniel, 1726-1801; Lavater, Johann Caspar, 1741-1801 -- Portraits; Lips, Johann Heinrich, 1758-1817
- Portraits, 1775-1816; Series I; 0.21; (.5 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Portraits is organized into Portraits of Johann Caspar Lavater and Portraits of Others.
  - PORTRAITS OF JOHANN CASPAR LAVATER
    - Wirz, J. H. [Johann Heinrich Wirz, 1784-1837?] Silhouette and manuscript motto, in printed borders and mounted. On one sheet, signed and dated Kilchberg, 1802 Sep 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Motto is dated 1 October 1790
    - Various artists. Etchings, engravings, and watercolors, including one with a manuscript inscription to Luise Lavater (his daughter) and a caricature depicting a Lavater-like figure presenting a light show. 14 items, 1775-1805, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Two by Johann Heinrich Lips, one by Daniel Chodowiecki
    - Various artists. Lavater memorials. Engravings, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Engraving of the memorial plaque at the St. Peterskirche in Zürich, engraving showing a monument to Lavater, with an explanatory printed broadsheet entitled "Erklärung zu Lavaters Denkmal. Gezeichnet und gestochen von J. H. Lips," printed poem, "Erinnerungen an J. K. Lavater," 4 pages
    - Unidentified. Etchings and engravings, including 2 engravings with the same manuscript caption in Lavater's hand on mount, and one full-length seated portrait. 5 pieces, undated
    - Unidentified. Silhouette showing two heads: Lavater and "Karg.", undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Identification according to a reproduction in the Speck bibliographical file
  - PORTRAITS OF OTHERS
    - Haid, I. I. Johann Jakob Bodmer (after a painting by Henry Fuseli). Engraving, undated
    - Lips, Johann Heinrich. "Wieland." Engraving, undated
    - Lips, Johann Heinrich. Engravings after works by other artists, including portraits of Condorcet, Salomon Schinz (1734-84) and Maximilian I. 7 items, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Schinz, Johann Caspar. Signed [self?]-portrait. Watercolor over pencil, 1816 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Schwerdgeburth, C. A. Carl Maria von Weber. Engraving, undated
    - Various artists. Portraits of Christoph Martin Wieland, Torquato Tasso, and Johann Caspar Schinz. Prints, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified. Engraving of Magdalena Lavater, infant. Mounted, with a manuscript caption in Lavater's hand, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified. Engraving of Johann Conrad Pfenninger (1747-1792). Mounted, with manuscript caption on mount, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified. Portrait of William Pitt the Elder. Pencil drawing with manuscript caption in Lavater's hand, 1798 Dec 10
      See YCGL MSS 6, vol. 817, for Lavater's commentary on Lips's bust of Pitt
    - Unidentified. Portrait of Anna Barbara Wolf Schulthess (1745-1818). Colored pencil and watercolor, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified. Silhouette of Katharina von Stolberg (1751-1832). Manuscript caption below, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Sister of Christian and Friedrich Leopold von Stolberg, undated
    - Unidentified. Portraits of Dante, St. Peter, and Judas (?); pastel with pen-and ink black medallions, and borders on blue background, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified. "Grosse Gesichtsform." Portrait of a man, ink drawing, mounted, with manuscript caption, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified. Four silhouettes, one a full-length portrait, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified. Four watercolor miniature portraits with manuscript captions in Lavater's hand, with matching borders and mounts, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Unidentified. Portfolio of portraits, unbound. 47 etchings with manuscript captions in the hand of Lavater interpreting facial expressions, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Mounted on 11 leaves of thick tan paper, most of them folded, with evidence that two others portraits have been torn away. With one sheet of etchings of horses. Several women are depicted, and a few of the portraits are identified as 17th-century personalities, including Ambrogio Spinola, Andreas Rivetus (Andrew Marvell), Jean Gaspard Gevaerts, Abraham Heidanus, and Pieter de Jode
    - Unidentified. Three prints of religious figures: young Christ, with manuscript motto by Lavater, dated 25 July 1796; Jesus with palm and crown of thorns, with manuscript motto by Lavater dated 8 May 1796; Samuel, with manuscript caption, 1796, undated
    - Unidentified. Three watercolor miniatures depicting religious figures, with manuscript captions in Lavater's hand, with matching borders and mounts, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Unidentified. Three watercolor miniatures: Portrait of a man, with manuscript caption "originalgenie des urbilds, wo in dem Bilde?", Man smoking, manuscript caption cropped, Boy reading outside, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Unidentified. Two watercolor portraits of women, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Unidentified. Two gouache portraits of men, one with caption in Lavater's hand, dated 12 July 1792; the other dated 15 November 1797, with a caption signed "G" (Georg Gessner?), 1792, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Other Artwork, 1776-1799; Series II; 0.6; (.75 box)
  Series II, Other Artwork, is organized into eight subseries: Jacques Callot, Daniel Chodowiecki, Johann Heinrich Lips, Conrad Meyer, Pfeninger, George Friedrich Schmol, Various Artists, and Unidentified.
  - CALLOT, JACQUES
    - Engravings, with engraved title "Diverse figures grotesques inventéees par Iacques Callot.... Paris [undated]" (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Engravings pasted on 16 sheets of paper folded into 4 signatures with folios numbered 17-48 (the last engraving is on leaf 44)
  - CHODOWIECKI, DANIEL
    - 18 small engravings, many of them signed by Daniel Chodowiecki, including two series of studies of heads, 1776, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Mounted on 4 sheets of tan paper (1 folded)
    - 16 small engravings and etchings of scenes, vignettes, and faces, many of them signed by Daniel Chodowiecki, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Mounted on 5 leaves of thick blue paper (one folded). Two engravings with manuscript captions in Lavater's hand interpreting the mood of the person portrayed
    - Three engravings and etchings, 1782, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Two etchings after Chodowiecki, in matching borders, with manuscript captions in Lavater's hand, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - LIPS, JOHANN HEINRICH
    - 16 engravings of scenes and vignettes, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Mounted on 7 leaves of gray paper, some folded as to form a booklet, with some page numbers between 11 and 39
    - Engravings after works by other artists. 9 items, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - [MEYER, CONRAD]
    - Four engraved scenes mounted on black cardboard with manuscript captions of two-line moral aphorisms in Lavater's hand mounted beneath, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
      One print by Conrad Meyer
  - PFENINGER, [----?]
    - "Horum est Regnum Dei." Two mezzotints after a painting by Benjamin West, with printed caption, two copies, each with a manuscript caption in Lavater's hand, undated
  - SCHMOL, GEORGE FRIEDRICH
    - "Nach der Natur im Spital zu Zürich gezeichnet." Pen-and-ink drawing of four heads, mounted with manuscript caption, 1779
      Also Schmoll, Schmohl
  - VARIOUS ARTISTS
    - Eight assorted engravings mounted on 4 sheets of tan paper, numbered nonconsecutively: literary scenes, portraits of Francis I and Maria Theresia, and a series of heads after Chodowiecki, undated
    - Miscellaneous engravings and etchings: vignettes, literary illustrations, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Six etchings (portraits, equestrian figures) mounted on two leaves of blue paper, one portrait with a manuscript caption in Lavater's hand, undated
  - UNIDENTIFIED
    - Four emblematic figures, with manuscript captions in Lavater's hand pasted below each. Watercolor over pen-and-ink, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Mounted inside matching folded leaves of blue paper, numbered 1, 44, 47, 48
    - Miscellaneous images, mounted: Jesus receiving children (watercolor over pen-and-ink), engraved portrait of a man, engraved page showing 16 heads of mammals, handpainted frame for medallion and motto, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Six emblematic etchings and watercolors, with manuscript captions in Lavater's hand, 1795-98 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Borders and mounting do not match each other. Three are dated: 29 April 1795; 12 September 1796; 1798
    - Three religious miniatures, including a colored portrait of St. Peter and a mounted engraving depicting Jacob and Joseph with a manuscript caption in Lavater's hand, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Two line drawings of heads, with manuscript captions in Lavater's hand; drawings on yellow background, mounted on blue-gray paper, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Two photographic reproductions of prints: Kaulbach's "Charlotte" and "Dora"; and one print of Pan, undated
    - Two religious epigrams in Lavater's hand, with similar borders and mounts; with colored miniature depicting a man, within the same border, 1799 Dec 4 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Other Papers, 1795-96; Series III; 0.1; (1 item)
  - Three manuscript texts in Lavater's hand, in handpainted borders, 1795-96 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Motto: Lerne lerneder stets die Kunst, den Moment zubenutzen. Poem: Lern' unaufhörlich mehr das Schädel ..., dated 6 May 1795. Poem: Junger Christus nach le Brun, dated 5 March 1796, for Anna Gessner-Lavater (Lavater's daughter)
- Oversize, 0.9; (1 box)
  - Unidentified. Etchings and engravings, including 2 engravings with the same manuscript caption in Lavater's hand on mount, and one full-length seated portrait. 5 pieces, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 37)
  - Haid, I. I. Johann Jakob Bodmer (after a painting by Henry Fuseli). Engraving, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 38)
  - Lips, Johann Heinrich. "Wieland." Engraving, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 39)
  - Schwerdgeburth, C. A. Carl Maria von Weber. Engraving, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 40)
  - Unidentified. Portrait of William Pitt the Elder. Pencil drawing with manuscript caption in Lavater's hand, 1798 Dec 10 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 41)
  - Unidentified. Three prints of religious figures: young Christ, with manuscript motto by Lavater, dated 25 July 1796; Jesus with palm and crown of thorns, with manuscript motto by Lavater dated 8 May 1796; Samuel, with manuscript caption, 1796, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 42)
  - "Horum est Regnum Dei." Two mezzotints after a painting by Benjamin West, with printed caption, two copies, each with a manuscript caption in Lavater's hand, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 43)
  - "Nach der Natur im Spital zu Zürich gezeichnet." Pen-and-ink drawing of four heads, mounted with manuscript caption, 1779 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 44)
  - Eight assorted engravings mounted on 4 sheets of tan paper, numbered nonconsecutively: literary scenes, portraits of Francis I and Maria Theresia, and a series of heads after Chodowiecki, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 45)
  - Six etchings (portraits, equestrian figures) mounted on two leaves of blue paper, one portrait with a manuscript caption in Lavater's hand, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 46)
  - Two photographic reproductions of prints: Kaulbach's "Charlotte" and "Dora"; and one print of Pan, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 47)
  - Jesus being led to his crucifixion, followed by a crowd. Ink drawing., undated (Box BSD, folder 48)